Hello, hello.
Perfect.
Hey guys, If you could just listen up real quick.
Hi, I'm Thomas.
I'm the semester speaker for DDCA Kent over there is the other one he's just type writing out his
e-mail onto the board.
So just wanted to let you guys know that if you have any questions, complaints, suggestions,
anything, don't hesitate to reach us to reach out to us.
And then we'll obviously like, you know, try to reach out to Professor Mutlu and like communicate
and kind of try to get your problems resolved.
And and yeah, that's about it from me.
I think if you also had a like send a message to the WhatsApp group, DDCA and like say Kent or
Thomas, like or semester speakers who would also reply and send your comments, complaints or yeah,
everything Great.
Thank you.
OK, you're right on time.
Yeah, yeah.
Please communicate with them for any feedback, positive or negative.
OK.
And you can read the e-mail address.
I cannot read it.
My eyes are not good.
But you guys are younger than me, so.
OK.
Are we ready?
I mean, all slides are OK, too.
OK, Today we're going to start timing and verification, which is yeah, that's OK, we can switch it
later, you know.
Yeah, in the in the second health.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Today we're going to start timing and verification, which is a really important topic especially
these days when you want to design both robust as well as high performance circuits.
So far we've assumed functional operation.
We didn't talk much about timing even though I showed you a couple of timing diagrams today.
We're going to actually really understand how to analyse the timing of both combinational and
sequential circuits.
But before we get into that, let's finish yesterday's lecture.
These are some of the readings that I recommend this week.
Next week we're going to actually go into architecture.
It's going to be a lot of fun.
We're going to raise the abstraction level.
We're going to be done with digital logic design.
We're going to talk about how a computer executes instructions.
How do we program it?
It's going to be the von Neumann model.
So it's going to be quite exciting, I think, and then we're going to bridge the gap later on.
But that's next week.
So let's wrap wrap up HDL, hardware description language and Verilog.
So remember we covered how to describe digital logic circuits, both combinational and sequential
using hardware description languages, specifically Verilog.
We covered a lot of syntax as well as semantics, and we discussed how you would describe a flip
flop, for example, right?
So hopefully you remember all of that.
If not, you're going to do a lot of that during lab.
So I'm sure you're going to be experts on how to do the basics of those at least, which is good,
which is part of it, But the principles are what matters.
I should really say that in the end, what you will take away from this course is how to think in
parallel, I would say, and that's the beauty of hardware.
When you design hardware, you will need to think about signals happening at the same time, going
everywhere, and you will need to think about that parallelism and think about the fact that things
are happening in parallel.
You need to have some way of synchronising things.
That's why we introduced the clock.
OK, so I also said yesterday that we will design some finite state machines based on what we learnt.
So that's what we're going to do first and then we're going to jump into timing and verification.
Does that sound good to everyone?
OK, cool.
So finite state machines, if you recall, it's essentially a discrete.
Model and it consists of three separate parts, and we're going to design these three separate parts
like we did with this smart traffic light.
If you remember, we could do that, but we're going to design a couple of other state machines.
You need essentially a state register to hold the state, and you need a next state logic to decide
what your next state will be.
And you need output logic to decide your outputs.
And at the beginning of the clock cycle, next state is latched into the state register and all of
that, all of those are available for the entire clock cycle as we discussed, right?
That's why this, we built the state register in the past.
So it consists of sequential circuits, state registers, combinational circuits, which are next state
logic and optic logic.
So we're going to design these three.
And you remember this design procedure that I went over when we discussed finite state machines.
You can read this.
I don't want to read this again, but we're going to develop it.
It's more interesting to develop it than just read this kind of text in a boring way.
OK, so this is the simple finite state machine we're going to design first, which is going to divide
the clock frequency by three.
Sometimes you don't want a clock frequency that's fast.
You want clock to be relatively short, let's say to be 1 relatively short.
And if you want to divide the clock frequency by three, this is what we want to achieve.
Basically this is that we have a fast clock, you want to divide it by three.
So you can see that 3 clock cycle become one clock cycle here.
The clock stays one for a two third, one third of that.
But that's not what's interesting to us in this particular case.
You can also try to do it such that clock stays one for half of that, but we're not going to do that
here.
The idea is the output wise high for one clock cycle out of every three.
In other words, the output device, the clock frequency, frequency of the clock by three.
So this is the state machine that your book designed and I took over here.
So there are three states S0S1S2 in S0, outputs of the clock, which is Y is 1.
Output of the circuit output of the FSM is 1.
And this is also the reset state.
This that's you need to have a reset state and finite state machines you have to be able to reset,
otherwise you will start from an unknown state and that's not good.
There's a common mistake that let's say rookies do when they start designing finite state machines,
they forget the reset state and then you have no idea where you would start from, right?
So don't forget the reset state and unconditionally at the next clock edge, you go to state one,
output becomes zero.
At the next clock edge, you go to state 2, out becomes 0, again, out to state zero, and then you go
to go back to state zero.
OK, this makes sense, hopefully based on what we're trying to achieve.
Now let's try to design it in Verilog.
Well, let's try to describe this in Verilog.
We designed it actually it's not.
It's not a hard design, as you can see.
So we call it divide by three FSM this module and we have a Reg variables.
These are stateful variables that we're going to assign that we're going to update at rising clock
edge, right state and next state.
And these are the parameters that we designed.
So basically we can you go back, the parameter descriptions are optional, but this is good for
encoding the states.
Basically state 0 is encoded AS00, state one is encoded as 01, state 2 is encoded AS10.
OK, this is the state register.
Now we're implementing the state register and you know how to implement it right now.
This happens to be a state register that is, that also has a reset as you can see, and it's
asynchronous reset.
Also it's it happens to be that it's sensitive to clock and reset over here, the positive edge of
clock and reset.
And if reset is 1, you reset the state.
In this example, it's different from what we have seen yesterday where a reset value of 0 reset the
state to 0 right here, a reset value of 1 reset the state to S0 on this particular case.
Again, that's a convention.
It's what you decide to do.
It's good to see different examples.
Otherwise, if reset is not one, then state becomes next state.
OK, so that's the idea over here.
This is what we implemented in the past also.
OK, and this is the next state logic.
How does next state get determined?
Remember, next state logic is combinational, right?
So we want some combinational logic, meaning always at whatever right hand side variable changes.
You basically set next state to a particular state encoding depending on your current state.
So for example, if your current state is S0, next state is assigned to be S 1 based on the FSMV
designed.
If your current state is S1, next state is assigned to be S2.
If your current state is S2, next state is assigned to be S0.
OK, this is combination.
As you can see this is.
And yesterday we discussed in detail why this is combinational.
OK, Basically this gets executed whenever any inputs on the right hand side changes and the output
always gets assigned something whenever that happens, OK?
That means it's a combinational circuit.
If you forgot in one of the assignments assigning next state, that wouldn't be combinational.
OK, and there's a default.
It's always good to have default even though you're never going to get to it.
Hopefully in this particular case, OK, again, it's good programming practice to have defaults.
OK, And the last one is output logic.
What is the output of this FSM?
Again, this is a combinational output.
In this particular case, the output is 1 only if the state is at 0, right?
Otherwise the output is 0.
So this is our output.
Let's, it's called Y as part of this module, and this turns out to be a machine FSN and FSM where
the output depends only on state.
And this happens to be a more type FSM.
As I said, I always confuse these, so it's always good to remember what is what.
If I ask you, I'm not going to ask you to memorise what's more type, What's mealy type?
I hate that sort of question that requires memorisation.
That's not very insightful, let's say.
So it's good to think about it, but it's more type FSM basically.
I checked it.
OK, so this is the full implementation.
Basically, I I built it part by part, but this is the full implementation of this divide by three
FSM that that divides the clock frequency by three.
Sounds good.
So if you want to reduce the frequency of your processor, you could add this FSM somewhere in your
machine and supply that clock to the rest of your machine.
And we're going to see that clock soon.
Any questions?
All good.
OK.
Oh, yes.
Why would you want to do it?
Because you want to save energy.
Remember when we discussed in the second lecture, power consumption is a function of capacitance
times voltage, square times frequency.
If you want to save energy, you want to reduce frequency.
And if you reduce frequency, you also you can also reduce the voltage, meaning you can actually get
a quad.
Yeah, you can actually get a cubic savings in energy by reducing the frequency.
And this is actually what microprocessors currently use to save energy.
If they're not doing something, let's say time critical, they reduce the frequency, they reduce the
voltage, they go slowly and save energy.
So this is a real circuit, even though it looks very simple.
OK, yes.
What would it sympathise the different circuit if we?
Good question.
I don't know, it depends on the synthesis tools probably OK, it will probably have the same
functionality, but I haven't thought about enough.
But this is good.
This is good for you to try and see.
Some of this is trial and error, you know, I don't know everything about the synthesis tools.
We're going to talk about the mapping also.
OK, very good.
So this is the other finite state machine that I will go through relatively quickly with.
So the question is, it may synthesize to something different, but it will have the same
functionality, right?
That's what you're asking.
But it wouldn't be more optimal or whatever.
More optimal in terms of what area, for example?
Yeah, again, you don't know the mapping.
So this is a description.
There's after this, there's a synthesis process and there's a mapping process and things get to the
circuit level in in, in this case, it's a very simple circuit.
So I don't expect there are a lot of issues frankly.
But if your question is for a larger circuit, that's very hard to tell, OK, You need to know the
underlying workings of the mapping and synthesis tools.
OK, So this is another state machine that we didn't cover, but I mentioned that you can take a look.
I'll go through this relatively quickly also, but I won't go into everything that's is going to
happen in the very long code.
Remember this snail that crawls down a paper tape with ones and zeros on it?
We very, very briefly talked about it in the FSM lecture, and the idea is this snail smiles whenever
the last four digits it has crawled over our 1101.
Someone decided that's an interesting problem.
Not that terrible, but it's kind of interesting to design finite state machines for it.
And essentially, if you design more and merely finite state machines for it, more means the output
of the machine is dependent only on the state.
Merely means the output of the finite state machine is dependent on on the state as well as the
input current input.
So a more machine looks like this.
Basically you have 5 states.
S0 is the reset state.
When you see a one, you go to.
S1, when you see another one after that you go to S2.
You've seen one one basically when you see another zero, you go to S3110 and when you see another
one, you go to S4 and output A1, OK, So this is the state where where you have seen 1101, OK?
And then if you see another one over here, you go back here because you're actually doing 1101
around that.
So you can optimise this machine basically and people have optimised whoever designed it, optimised
it.
So you have 5 states.
On the other hand, the mealy version of this has four states.
That's usually the case if If your outputs depend on the state, you usually have more states.
Whereas if your outputs depend on not only the state but also the inputs, you can reduce the number
of states.
You have an F finite state machine because you're more richer in terms of the encoding of the output
information.
You don't need as many states as outputs essentially.
OK, so if you look over here, this is also doing the same thing in a different way.
So you're you're an S0.
You get an input of 1, you see a one.
Basically you output 0 because you haven't seen 1101 yet.
You go to S1 and then you you get another one.
You've seen one, one.
Basically at that point you output 0 because you haven't seen 1101 yet.
So you go to S2, you see a zero, you go to S3 and you output A1 because you've seen 110 but not 1101
yet.
And then if you're in S3 and if you see a one, you go to S1.
Essentially at that point you've seen 1101 and you output A1.
OK.
And the reason you go to S1 is you optimise the OK, you could have gone somewhere else, but then you
have more states, right?
OK, so you can convince yourself that these things work and we're going to implement in this case
the Mealy machine in the very long code, we're going to do something very similar.
Basically these are you have state and next state variables as regs and you have the input clock
reset digit that you're seeing and whether you're smiling or not, that's the output one bit output.
And these are the four state encoding S0 through S3.
This is essentially the state register, which is exactly the same as what we've seen earlier.
It's asynchronous reset, pause the edge clock triggered register and reset is active, ends one, and
this is the next state logic, which is again describing what's happening over here, right?
It's activated always.
It's also a combination logic.
If you're in state zero and if you see a digit, the next state is S1.
Otherwise the next state is S0.
OK, you stay in S0 because you haven't seen one yet.
If you're in S1 and if you've seen a digit, next stage S2.
Otherwise you go back to S0 because it's as if you haven't seen anything.
You're starting from scratch.
And you can you can again convince yourself that this is correct or look at your book, OK, And that
that was the next state logic output logic is also combinational.
And in this case, the question is whether or not you're smiling.
And in this particular case, if you're in state S3 and if you see a digit, then you basically output
a smile, OK?
That's the only case where you Optus to smile.
Does that sound good?
OK, So in this case, output depends on state and input.
So it's a mealy type FSM and we use simple combination assignment.
In this case, we have only four states.
You could actually implement the same thing with more states.
It's easy to make more states.
The problem is your circuit becomes larger, right?
But this is, I believe minimal in this particular case for a mealy type FSM, OK.
And this is the full implementation of this smiling snail sounds good.
In your labs, you'll do a lot of FSM implementation.
So it'll be a lot of fun.
OK, So I think we're done with HDL and Verilog right now.
We in this last part of this lecture, which is really carrying over from yesterday, we described
sequential circuits.
We talked about the always statement, which is interesting.
It's good to to try this and learn more about this.
We talked about blocking and non blocking statements and we talked about describing FSMS today.
Now we're going to talk about how to look at timing and how to test circuits.
Are people ready or are there questions?
Ready Sounds like ready.
OK, so let's talk about timing and verification.
This is going to be a lower level lecture because we're going to talk about timing, but we're still
not not going to go below the logic level.
We're going to assume timing, timing associated with different logic gates, for example.
And I think your book does a nice job.
So I will I will still recommend you look at your book if you want more information on this.
So we're going to start with timing in combinational circuits.
We're going to introduce some notions of propagation delay and contamination delay, which are
essentially going to what we're going to use to analyze timing we're going to talk about.
Glitches.
And then we're going to talk about sequential circuits, which will build on what we introduce here,
but also add sequential components to it.
And we're going to talk about how to determine how fast a circuit can operate, meaning the clock
cycle of a circuit of a sequential circuit.
Clock cycle makes sense for a sequential circuit, of course, right?
Not a combinational circuit, because combinational circuit doesn't have the notion of a state or
clock cycle.
But we'll start with combinational elements because those are needed for sequential circuits.
And then we're going to switch gears and talk about circuit verification, which is how to make sure
a circuit works correctly, which is a difficult problem, which is becoming increasingly difficult
today because the sizes of the transistor that we're building are becoming smaller and smaller.
OK, so let's talk about some trade-offs in circuit design.
Basically, there's a lot that we want in circuit design.
When you ask the question, for example, optimal, what is optimal?
What is the metric that we're optimising for?
Area is one of them, right?
Circuit area is really proportional to the cost of the device.
Speed, Speed can be expressed in terms of latency, throughput, frequency.
We're going to talk more about that when we talk about the execution time of programs performance.
In general, we want faster, more capable circuits to achieve more right, to do more power and energy
consumption.
Mobile devices need to work with limited power supply.
Actually everything needs to work with limited power supply.
Today, high performance devices dissipate a lot of they have very high power density, which is watts
per centimetre square for example.
So we need to care a lot about this today especially.
And then design time is also important.
These are some of the metrics only there.
You can add more metrics over here, of course, like time to failure could be one metric, but we're
not going to talk about that today.
Design time, designers are expensive in terms of time and time and money.
Testing is expensive.
And if you're actually competing for some reason, whatever reason, the competition will not wait for
you.
Don't expect that.
Don't expect them to slow down.
Basically, even if you slow down.
So there are many, many requirements and goals and we know that they depend on the application,
depend defining different computing platforms.
In the end circuit timing effects all of these, right?
So, so far we've investigated logic functionality, you talked about functional behaviour.
We haven't talked about timing behaviour.
Now the question becomes today, well, how fast is a circuit?
How can we make it faster?
What happens if we run too fast?
You get wrong results.
Basically, that's a good answer, but why does why do you get wrong results and how far, how far you
can push the circuit to run fast and what do you care about while doing that?
So essentially there's a distinction between functional and timing, right?
You may actually have a perfectly functional circuit, but if you don't care about the timing, you
may set the clock frequency to some value where the circuit doesn't operate, right?
So today we're going to enable the circuit circuits to operate so that they're implementable.
So we'll start with combinational circuit timing.
As I said, this is an important picture to keep in mind.
I showed you this multiple times.
I'm going to show you multiple times again.
Basically, we're going to start with the timing of the combinational logic.
But this combinational logic is part of any kind of sequential circuit.
Also, if you remember right, we just built an FSM which had multiple combinational logic blocks,
right?
Which was like this, for example.
This is actually a more type FSM where the output is dependent on the on the on the state, for
example.
And the next state logic is over here.
So there are two combinational logic blocks.
This is something we're going to talk a lot about.
There's a pipeline type of circuit, but we're going to analyse the timing of one part of it where
you actually have inputs coming from this state register and going through the combinational logic
and being latched in the next state register.
And if the combination logic delay is larger than your clock cycle delay, you will latch the wrong
result, right?
That's why combination logic delay is going to be important, OK?
Hopefully that's gives you the bigger picture because we want to set our clock cycle such that this,
any combination logic delay that we have in the system is not larger than the clock cycle.
But we will see that that invariance is not going to be enough.
We need to care about other things also.
OK, so essentially this is the logic, the community abstraction.
And so far we've assumed that output changed immediately when the input changes.
Looks like this, right?
When A falls, Y rises, right?
Unfortunately, that's not the case in real life.
Outputs are delayed from the inputs.
Transistors take a finite amount of time to switch, and it kind of looks like this.
When A rises, it's not a sharp rise, it takes time to actually rise.
So there's some delay as A goes from zero to 1, zero to VDD, for example high voltage, and there's
another delay from.
A transitioning from zero to 1 and Y starting to change and finishing to change.
OK, And that's really the delay of this inverter over here.
Well, in this case, it's a buffer, sorry.
So it's not an inverter, but you could make it an inverter and this will go down right the other
way.
I'm too used to murders.
OK, so this is a real delay example from some simulations from some paper.
I kind of like this because it also shows that delay is statistical, right?
You basically your delay doesn't isn't always the same.
It changes across time, it changes across temperature, it changes across voltage.
There are a lot of things that affect the circuit timing delay.
And also it it's it's it it it also is depend on whether your input is 0 or one as well.
So for example, this work shows that going from if the input goes from a 90% voltage level high to
for the output to transition by 10% to the lower level, it takes this this many nanoseconds, right?
If you, if you look at the 50% levels or if the input is at 50% over here for the output to go down
to 50% while the input is going up to 50%, it's about 0.169 nanoseconds, right.
So even the delay, the statistical property, that's what I'm getting at over here.
How do you define delay becomes important?
So in general what people do is they measure and they figure out a worst case delay for a gate that
is designed and they basically report you the worst case delay such that you can assume that, but
under different conditions, delay can be different for different voltages, for example.
So if you want to optimise your circuit, you may actually want to change the delay analysis that you
do based on different voltages, different temperatures, etcetera.
OK, so we're going to simplify a lot of that.
Look at one version of delay, OK.
So delay is what is delay fundamentally caused by Essentially any circuit elements has some
capacitance and some resistance, right?
And when current needs to flow, it's needs to go against that resistance.
And that actually delays the flow of electrons.
And in the end, you're limited by some sort of physical phenomena.
There's finite speed of light, right?
And unfortunately the speed of light is something that we're very close to at the nanosecond level,
right?
We're operating at nanosecond levels and speed of light is not travelling as fast, OK.
So a lot of things can change the delay, whether input is changing from zero to one or one to zero,
whether it's rising or falling.
You may have different input values or different input variables that lead to different delays.
We will see some of that change in the environment like temperature, humidity.
These things may affect the delay circuit delay ageing of the circuit, how old it is, may affect the
delay.
Voltage supplied to the circuit certainly affects the delay.
Higher voltage usually enables faster flow.
As a result, you, you can operate faster, right?
Lower voltage, lower energy, lower mobility.
As a result, you're slower.
That's why energy is also lower with lower voltage.
OK, so basically you have a range of possible delays from input to output.
But now let's take a look at analysis that we will do.
Keep this in mind, we're not going to talk a whole lot about all of these variables, right?
But keep that in mind that it's more complex than what we have.
So in the end, if you want to really have a circuit that operates under all possible conditions that
you could imagine, you really need to take these into account.
And it's not easy to take these into account.
So what's people do is people do the timing analysis that we're going to do.
On top of that, they add a timing margin, margin saying that, OK, I did my timing analysis to the
best I can, but I don't know all of the conditions that happen under which the circuit will
operate.
So I'm going to add another 30% delay to the maximum delay that I get in my maximum combination
logic delay.
This is very common practice.
30% is not an unreasonable number.
In some cases it's 40 percent, 50%.
OK, So this doesn't mean that the circuit really needs that long, but the design is unsure about the
conditions under which the circuit will operate.
So a lot of the circuits may be operating slower than they could on their regular conditions.
So what some smart people do who care about their performance, some of these happen to be gamers,
for example, What they do is they basically increase their clock frequency because they may know
that in under their conditions the circuit will operate fine, right?
OK.
So it's good to think about this so you can be smart about how you operate your circuitry also.
OK, so let's talk about some.
Variable some some definitions.
So we're we're we're trying to find the delay from input to output Y.
We're going to call output Y contamination delay.
This is also called the minimum delay TCD.
This is the delay until Y starts changing.
OK, and there's propagation delay.
And this is the delay until Y finishes changing.
So you change the input at some point the output starts changing and at some point output finishes
changing.
So there's a range.
So the one is the minimum delay, the other is the maximum delay.
OK, so let's take a look at that example combinational circuit.
You have two inputs AB and output Y.
Let's take, let's take a look at the effect of changing input A.
So input A starts changing at this point and output Y starts changing at this point.
After that that this cross hatching means value is changing.
You don't you cannot trust that value.
So you can see that contamination delay is over here.
After A is changing, Y starts changing somehow and propagation delay is when Y finishes changing.
So the input is guaranteed to be stable at that point.
OK, so we're going to see examples of this contamination and propagation delay right now.
So what we want is we want to calculate the longest and shortest delay path.
We care about both of them.
And we will see why shortest is important also soon.
Normally we talk about the longest delay path, right?
But shortest is also important.
So let's take a look at this.
Longest delay path is also called critical path.
So you take a combinational logic critical path is the longest delay path in that combinational
logic.
And the critical path of an entire microprocessor is the longest critical path that you have in any
combinational logic delay in a sequential system, basically.
So let's take a look at this particular simple combination logic over here.
You have 4 inputs, ABCD, and you have Y.
Thinking about just the gate delays, This is our short path, right?
When D changes, Y starts changing after some point, and that's your minimum delay for that change to
start happening, right?
This is our contamination delay.
Basically here critical path is over here, it happens either with A or B.
This is the longest delay after which Y will finish changing, right?
So let's take a look at that.
So our shortest path, it's easier to see perhaps over here contamination delay is the contamination
delay that happens through this and gate.
We're going to ignore wires have delays for now.
It's a bad assumption, but for now, let's ignore that, OK?
Wires complicate things a lot because it's very hard to assign these delays to wires because when
you map the circuit that you describe in a language in hardware description language to a lower
level hardware, those wires get routed also.
So the tools that do that mapping actually optimise those wires, and you may not have a very good
idea at the higher level in terms of the delay of the wires.
OK, Delay of the gates, it's a bit easier, OK, Assuming the tools actually map to these gates, of
course, right?
So the shortest path is from D to Y, and there's an AND gate after D starts changing, Y starts
changing after some point, and that's our contamination delay for the AND gate.
So there should be a value for that contamination delay for the AND gate that someone provides to
us, OK.
OK.
So the longest path in this case is the propagation delay from this inputs, any of the inputs to the
output of the circuit goes through one AND gate one OR gate another AND gate, right?
So essentially 2 AND gates plus one OR gate the longest delay that you can have in any of these two
propagation delay of the AND gates plus one propagation delay of the OR gate.
OK, so every circuit component has two delays, CD and PD.
Contamination delay is the shortest delay that you can have from the input to the output, the input
changing to the output starting to change.
Propagation delay is the delay that you will have from the input changing to the output finishing to
change.
Right?
There are two delay components for each gate.
OK, two delay values.
So let's take a look at this.
This is from your book.
Also, I like this example.
So assume that initial values are 1101 for ABCD and a goes from 1 to 0.
This is what happens.
A goes from 1 to 0.
After some point this N1 changes, starts changing and then finishes changing and then N2 starts
changing and then finishes changing and then Y starts changing and then finishes changing.
So you can see that this is sequential dependence on prior values.
So that's our critical path basically.
And this is the shortest path.
Short path when D goes from 1 to 0, Y switches from 1 to 0, but it takes some time and that's the
shortest path.
That we have OK, OK, so let's take a look at an example TPD.
So someone provides you these values and then you can do this analysis.
And I pick this picture.
How many people use this stuff?
These are OK.
These are real gates actually, that you could put.
These are huge technology.
It's not it's not what we have in microprocessors today.
But you can put these on bread boards and you can design your own circuits.
You can build a microprocessor.
It's a lot of fun to do this and whenever you buy the stuff, you get a data sheet that tells you the
delay characteristics so that you can design A circuit that matches whatever your requirements that
you may want to satisfy.
And you can see that the propagation delay, for example for this two input NAND gate is specified
not so easily, meaning the propagation delay NA.
So inputs are AB to Y.
And then there's a figure over here.
I guess that's the figure, or maybe that's not the figure, I don't know.
But anyway, the propagation delay is dependent on voltage.
It's dependent on temperature, as you can see, right?
So for example, if your voltage is huge at 25°C, your delay is only 7 nanoseconds, which is not bad
for this huge circuit.
But if your voltage is lower, like 2 volts and you're operating at pretty high temperature, your
delay is pretty long, 135 nanoseconds.
So basically there's heavy dependence on voltage and temperature and somebody determines your these
delays.
How to determine these delays is the subject of another course.
OK, again, microelectronics design.
But here we assume that we get these delays.
OK, now let's take a look at the worst case delay of a four to one multiplexer.
You guys love 4 to 1 multiplexers, right?
We've seen that multiple times today.
And now let's take take a not today in the past, we're going to construct different types of four to
one multiplexers and look at their delays, different implementations essentially.
And these are the gates that we're given.
For example, I have a knot gate propagation delays, 32 input and 63 input and 80...
OK.
This is the circuit components that I gate that I'm given as gates.
This is 1 implementation that you've seen in the past.
You can see that this has four, three inputs and gates, 4 input or gates and two inverters, right?
And this is a multiplexer.
Hopefully you realise that.
And now if you want to look at the propagation delay, forget about the contamination delay, right?
Now you want to find the critical path.
And the critical path is the longest delay path that goes through the most number of gates, right?
So in this case, for example, S1 going through this inverter and then going through this and gate
and then going through this or gate is 1 critical path that also applies to S0, for example.
OK, so essentially the propagation delay is the delay of the inverter, the delay of the three input
and gate plus the delay of the three input and gate plus the delay of the four input or gate
308090.
That's 200 picoseconds in this description.
OK, So there could be another propagation delay that may be important.
So that's the S path.
There's also AD path that goes through D1 gate, 1/3 input end gate, and then outputs 14 input OR
gate.
That's essentially one end gate and one OR gate.
And you can convince yourself that that's 80 + 91170 picoseconds, which is lower than 200
picoseconds.
So that's not our critical path.
That's a shorter path.
OK, so this is another implementation of the four to one multiplexer which uses inverters, 2 inputs
and gates to control the enable input of a tri-state buffer and four tri-state buffers.
OK, now let's take a look at the critical path over here again, I will take s S gets inverted 1
inverter delay, one delay through the two input and gates and one delay through the enable input to
the output of the tri-state buffer, right?
So that's essentially 30 picoseconds for the inverter, 60 picoseconds for the two input and gates
and enable to why delay of the tri-state is specified as 35 picoseconds.
So that's 125 picoseconds.
OK, if you actually look at the delay over here, these happens to be supplied earlier over here.
As you can see, that's that goes to only an invert, only a tri-state buffer, because you're really
gating the tri-state, gating the D signals to the output based on the values of S1S0, essentially,
right?
That's what we're doing over here.
So the delay from D to output is actually very fast, 50 picoseconds.
That's not enough.
On our critical path.
So if you want to do this critical path analysis, and if it's not immediately obvious to you what's
the critical path, you take every single input, figure out the propagation delay from that input to
the output, and you basically look which value is the highest.
In this particular case, 125 picoseconds is the highest because that's the delay from S1 to output,
longest delay from S1 to output.
But it turns out to be better than 200 picoseconds over here, right?
This sounds nice.
So I would take this implementation maybe, maybe not because I didn't consider the wire delays over
here.
So there is some capacitance on this wire that's probably a bit higher than the capacitance that I
would get in this output.
So the delay over here may be a little bit longer actually, right.
So whenever you're getting the delays of a tri-state buffer, it doesn't tell you the delays on about
how many other tri-state buffers are connected to the wire, right?
So we didn't take that capacitance into account.
So there are some limitations to our methodology as you can see, but this is not a bad approximation
to begin with for our purposes.
OK, so clearly one observation over here is different designs lead to very different delays.
Now this is the importance of doing this sort of analysis right now.
I'll give you another design over here with some assumptions from your book, which leads to even
different delays.
This is actually a completely tri-state buffer based implementation.
And you can, if you trust your book, this is the delays that you would get.
I'll let you study it on your own.
But this turns out to be again, a bit faster than the previous ones.
But it's also assumed that the inversion happens for free inside the tri-state buffer.
So it's good to think about that.
And this may be a bit better because the loading on the wires may be a bit better actually, which
are which we don't take into account.
OK, so essentially here you go through different tri-state buffers and at most you have two
tri-state buffer delays, OK, OK, so that's the third implementation.
OK, So essentially it's not always this easy to determine the long short paths.
Not all input transitions affect the output.
You can have multiple different paths from an input to an output.
So you'll need to really do the analysis such that you don't miss the longest possible path, right?
And in this particular case, these are simple circuits.
You can see the longest possible path perhaps, right?
But if it's a very complicated circuit, very complicated combination logic with 1000 inputs and
maybe, I don't know, 50 outputs, it doesn't become that's easy.
It's not that easy basically.
And also a different instance of the same gates may have different delays because we're assuming the
gates have same delay, right?
But when you manufacture them, there's actually manufacturing process variation.
So some gates are actually smaller, some gates are bigger because you, we can, we don't know how to
perfectly manufacture things.
This is true for everything, right?
You've got these chairs over here.
Are they all exactly the same?
Not really, right?
There's a lot of variation over here, actually different rooms over here, even though they are
designed to be very similar, potentially they're still different from each other.
So there's manufacturing variation that happens in some cases that variation is quite high actually.
So this assumption doesn't hold necessarily.
So it becomes a more statistical analysis than what we've done so far.
Wires, we've already discussed this.
They have non zero delay.
That's a big assumption that we've made over here.
They have zero delay.
Again, temperature, voltage, not all circuit elements are affected the same way.
Also some elements are affected more when the temperature changes.
Some of them are affected less depending on how they're built.
This could even change the critical path potentially depending on how things behave.
So you may need to actually think a lot more on the analysis.
So in general what people do is they assume the worst case conditions, worst temperature, worst
voltage, OK, lowest voltage, highest temperature.
But they may also have bins because what current processors do is they do something called dynamic
voltage and frequency scaling.
And when they actually change the voltage, and they also can do it on at different temperatures,
they can also change the frequency.
So what a designer needs to do is under different conditions, determine the worst case delay and
decide on a clock frequency.
OK, so it's actually, there's a lot of statistics involved in deciding the real clock frequency.
OK, so this is a summary of our combinational timing.
Essentially, circuit outputs change sometime after the inputs change.
This is caused by multiple things, finite speed of light.
In the end, delays depend on inputs, environmental state, etcetera.
And we studied two major things.
Contamination, delay.
This is the minimum.
Possible delay, it's good to think about it that way.
TCD and propagation delay, maximum possible delay from the input to the output.
And this could be done on a gate level, this could be done on a combinational circuit level.
And delays change with circuit design, operating conditions, etcetera.
Before I go into sequential circuits, I want to introduce those output glitches because you will see
these glitches when you design your circuits.
But before that, any questions on combinational delay?
Yes.
Yeah, I mean it could be both.
So if you over clock, there are multiple issues, right.
Basically, you're, you're increasing the frequency, reducing the clock cycle time.
You're operating the circuit much faster and you may latch some, you may actually latch some result
that's incorrect because you didn't give the circuit enough time, right?
That could be one reason.
The other reason is you're operating the circuit faster.
Temperature was also increasing and you actually your, your likelihood of latching something wrong
also increases.
I mean, there could be multiple reasons, but latching wrong results is a very good reason to get
wrong, to get a crash, for example, or to get something undesirable while you're playing a game.
You thought you were actually winning the game and you may start losing it because something, the
score, the score got lashed in the wrong way, right?
It's gonna happen.
OK, so before we move to sequential circuits, let's talk about output glitches.
You will see a lot of this.
This is actually a fun topic for me, but OK, this is related to what you kind of asked, but glitch
is a little bit different, right One one problem that you may have is you latch some wrong result.
So you didn't give enough time, you calculated the delay wrong, let's say in combination logic.
As a result, you latch some wrong results at the clock edge.
And that could easily happen when you over clock things.
I'm going to finish out with glitches and then we're going to take a break.
And OK, what was I saying?
So that's one possible reason.
So another possible reason is you have a glitch, and somehow you didn't take that glitch into
account, and then you latch the wrong result.
OK, what's a glitch?
Glitch means one input transition causes multiple output transitions.
So let's take a look at the circuit.
This circuit's initial state looks like this.
You have 00 inputs over here, one over here.
The output is one right?
Now if this transitions, OK, if this transitions from one to zero, what does this go to 1 to 1?
So there are actually 2 paths that this input effects, right?
One is the fast path and the other is the slow path over here.
OK, something is wrong over here.
But this should be 1 I think 011 OK Anyway, this is correct.
This part is correct.
Meaning this is transitioning from 1 to 0.
Initially these are zeros, initially this is 01/1 and this transitioning from one to zero and this
will transition from one to something.
OK, so there are two paths over here.
When this transitions to 0, this gate becomes zero and this may change, right?
OK.
And when this transitions, the slow path doesn't get updated as quickly.
So as a result, the output over here goes from 1 to 0 back to one.
OK, makes sense.
Hopefully you can verify that.
OK, so the issue is OK, this is the picture over here.
B is transitioning from one to zero and two changes from one to zero.
OK.
Because initially it's one and then it becomes zero quickly and N1 goes up a little bit later.
But after N2 changes over here, Y goes to zero, OK.
And only after N1 goes up, Y goes back up to one, OK.
So for a short period of time, while this output, this N1 is propagating, you get a glitch, meaning
Y output becomes 0.
OK, now this may not be a problem if your clock cycle is long enough, but this becomes a problem if
you somehow set your clock cycle too close to this glitch such that you latch the zero over here,
right?
You don't want to latch the zero because the circuit didn't have enough time to evaluate.
If you didn't do your timing, alas, collect correctly, you can actually have a glitching problem.
OK, you can.
You can, You don't, basically.
You don't want to have the glitch affect your state.
That's a simple way of putting it.
Glitches should not affect your state.
OK, so when could a glitch be bad?
Basically, I gave you the question if I gave you the answer if if it affects your state, if the if
the output of a glitch, if the result of a glitch gets latched in a state register.
OK, so how do you avoid glitches?
The essentially you add redundancy to the circuit.
We didn't talk about K maps, but I'll give you a very quick example of what AK map is because it's
fun to think about it.
Essentially, K maps are a pictorial depiction of the truth table, right?
So this is what we had, right?
If you think about it, this is a bar, B bar.
This is BC.
OK, so if you actually write the truth table in a pictorial way of this circuit, why this is our
output pictorially described AB IS00011110C is 01, output is 1 if a bar B bar is true, meaning A is
0 and B is 0 or if BC is true.
So this is the case where BC is true and this is the case where a bar B bar is true.
This is a beautiful pictorial representation of a truth table which we didn't cover.
These are called Carnot maps, K maps.
I'm not going to ask you questions about it, but the reason which happens is kind of visible in this
pictorial representation.
You're moving from here to here, meaning while.
So B is changing from one to zero and A is staying at zero and C is staying at one, essentially.
OK, so how to eliminate it?
Basically, you can eliminate it by adding a little bit more redundancy in hardware, adding this
term, and this term happens to be a bar C OK, so you can fix the glitch, meaning you can get rid of
that glitch completely by adding one more gate over here, a bar C.
And this way there will be no case where this Y will go from one to zero M back to one.
OK, it's interesting to think about.
I gave you one way of thinking about it, but you can also think about it by reasoning about the
truth table, right?
So I'll let you think about this because this actually this takes a little bit of time to think
about.
So the issue was our circuit glitched because it had some cases where one of the variables affected
the output quickly, right?
You can reduce that by actually adding another term, yes.
Will it be cheaper to add?
OK, that's a great question.
Yes.
So that's another possibility.
You could add buffer, yes.
Then you need to balance the buffers.
So you're proposing an implementation solution here.
It's a more logical solution.
Does that make sense?
But very good, keep that in mind because we're going to add those buffers for another reason.
But yes, you could also add a buffer over here, but then getting the timing may be more difficult.
OK, so in this case, there is no dependence on B, so there is no glitch.
That's essentially how we eliminated this glitch.
So do we always care about glitches?
Basically, not always, but sometimes it's a bit dangerous, right?
If you're actually pushing your frequency too much and the glitch happens too close to the end of
the clock cycle, you may actually have a a danger of latching this glitch, right?
That's the danger we have basically.
And fixing them is undesirable.
It consumes area, consumes power, more design effort in general.
We don't want to fix that.
So in the end, if you set your frequency right, the circuits should operate correctly regardless of
glitches.
The key is really setting your frequency right.
So basically the take away is not always we can safely ignore glitches, but we need to be able to
doing the timing analysis right if we want to ignore the glitches.
OK, so when you see glitches in your simulation, up input output and you will see them when you
design your circuits, it's important to recognise them as glitches and it's important to not to let
them affect your state.
And that brings me to state.
But this is a good place to take a break.
Let's be back at 1520 and then we're going to talk about sequential circuit timing.
So now that we've covered combinational timing, let's talk about sequential circuit timing, which is
the even more exciting part, let's say.
And I'll show you this picture again.
So we've covered the combinational logic.
Now we're going to look at what happens in A in a sequential circuit where you have state registers
as inputs as well as the outputs.
OK.
And that's going to be more realistic because that's going to be our designs going into the future.
And we're going to talk about D flip flop.
We're going to abstract it a little bit.
You can do the analysis of the D flip flop yourself, but essentially remember the D flip flop, we
built it so that we can sample D at the rising clock edge and it outputs the sampled value to Q and
it stores or keeps the sampled value until the next rising clock hitch, right?
That's how this operates and it's made from combinational elements.
And all of these DQ clock all have timing requirements.
And we looked at one implementation of the flip flop in the in the last lecture.
If you remember right, 2D latches put together first latch, second latch and the inverted clocks
applied to the first one as right enable and the non inverted clocks applied to the second one as
right enable signal.
That's one implementation.
But D flip flop can have multiple different types of implementations.
So that's why we're going to abstract it and we're going to treat it as as an element that's
basically samples D and outputs Q.
And this happens at a clock edge.
It could be at the rising clock edge or falling clock edge, it doesn't matter.
We're going to assume rising.
And the question becomes when should D be stable and when is Q available, right?
And what we're going to do is we're going to introduce some timing constraints to this D flip flop.
And we're going to say the input D must be stable when it's sampled, meaning at the rising clock
edge.
But that's not enough because there's some delay internally in this thing, right?
You can think of this as I like thinking of this as a camera.
I think one of your books has this also, whenever you take a picture with a camera, there's some
aperture time, right, where the camera takes light in.
And all of during all of that time, the camera gets exposed.
You can think of flip flop taking a picture of the right.
It's basically taking a picture and sampling.
If D is not stable during any time in the picture, you may get a fuzzy value or the wrong value,
right?
OK, because there's some internal delay associated with it.
This flip flop is not essentially it's it's consists of combinational elements.
So we're going to call this time where the flip flop where the input needs to be stable as aperture
time.
And there are actually two things over here.
1 is the set up time and the other is the hold time of the flip flop.
So set up time or T set up is the time before the clock edge.
That data must be stable.
Data should not be changing after this point.
OK, if it changes, you may capture the wrong value.
Hold time is time after the clock edge that data must be stable.
OK, we're going to see why hold time is important soon.
OK, so these two are important and together this is called the aperture time of the deep loop flop.
Inspired by this camera again, time around the clock edge.
That data must be stable.
TA is equal to C set up plus C hold, but we usually divide it into two set up and hold.
And we're going to analyse things in a different way, as you will see.
OK, so before I go into how to do the analysis, I should introduce this meta stability.
I'll go through this relatively quickly.
Essentially, if D is changing when it's sampled, some meta stability can occur.
Flip flop output is stuck somewhere between 1 and 0, and output eventually settles non
deterministically.
So this is an example of meta stability that people have simulated for AN and Rs latch, for example.
It's true for AD flip flop also because the D flip flop is usually made of latches.
So here this is your output.
There's your input where you violated the timing and when the clock falls with the falling edge
triggered the flip flop.
Essentially, when the clock falls, you go into some metastable state between zero and one, as you
can see, and based on different conditions of the circuit, you may settle to one or you may settle
to zero, OK, because you change things while the flip flop is sampling things, OK, too, too close
to the clock edge, basically.
OK.
So it's good to think about that.
There's a lot of research on that area.
OK, So this is the output timing that we're going to assume with the flip flops.
So I'm going to introduce a couple of terms, but they're going to be contamination delay and
propagation delay again.
So this is clock.
There's a clock to queue delay that happens.
So we talked about the data delay that needs to be satisfied, input data delay, that's the setup
time and the whole time.
But there's also, when we do the timing analysis, there will be a clock to queue delay.
This is CCQ, essentially clock to queue delay, contamination delay, contamination, clock to queue.
And then there's propagation clock to queue, OK.
This is the same thing basically what we discussed earliest time after the clock edge, that queue
starts to change.
That's CCQ, OK.
And then there's PCQ, which is propagation delay, clock to queue.
That's the latest time after the clock edge that queue stops changing.
That's the worst case delay.
This is the shortest delay, OK, Very similar to combinational logic, except we apply it to clock to
queue input for the flip flop clock clock input to queue output because it also consists of
combinational components, right?
OK, there's no magic inside.
You could actually do this analysis yourself for a given flip flop design, which we're not going to
do now, but we're going to assume, OK.
So recall, this is one example of a sequential system design.
So what we have discussed, all of those delays set up time, hold time, clock to queue, contamination
and propagation delays affect the sequential circuit where you have inputs in register one and some
combinational logic operates on those inputs and the result of the combination logic needs to be
placed into register 2 at the rising edge of the clock.
So you have one full clock cycle.
The question is essentially, how do you decide that clock cycle such that you don't latch incorrect
data violating the timing, OK?
Essentially you have multiple flip flops that are connected with combination logic.
Clock runs with a period TC, that's the cycle time.
How long is your clock cycle time?
It's essentially when the clock rises the first time and when the clock rises the next time.
That's your clock cycle time.
The distance in terms of time between those two rising edges, OK, Essentially for this to work, you
must meet timing requirements for both register one as well as register two.
OK, Combination logic has some timing, but there are also timing requirements that you have for
register one and register two.
OK, we're ignoring wires still.
There are also wires, but let's ignore them.
So how do we ensure correct sequential operation?
Essentially, we need to ensure correct input timing on R2 to begin with, right?
This is our register 2, meaning that what you latch here should be correct.
You should not latch something too quickly before the combination logic settles.
You should not latch something during the whole time.
You should not violate the whole time and you should not violate the set up time.
Basically, something should not change after the clock edge for some time.
OK, so the results over here that go into R2D2, essentially D2 should be stable during the whole
time as well as the set up time or during the set up time and the hold time.
OK, OK, so essentially that's what I what I meant what I said over here.
So this is your clock edge, rising clock edge D2.
This D2 over here must be stable at least T set up before the clock edge so that you don't violate
the set up time requirements and it should be stable at least until T hold time after the clock
edge.
OK.
And that's your aperture time makes sense.
If it changes, you may get a get meta stability or some wrong value.
You have the same requirement over here compared to the previous stage, let's say previous whatever
combination logic over here.
But we're going to do the analysis over here.
So whatever I said actually has implications on the entire clock cycle time now and we're going to
do that analysis now.
This means that there is both a minimum and maximum delay between the two flip flops.
SO2 flip flops we're talking about is R1 the that's has the inputs and R2 that stores the output at
the rising clock edge.
So this is what we're going to look at essentially.
So if for example, combination logic over here is too fast, what happens is this D2 changes too fast
and it may violate the whole time over here, OK, because the clock clock rises over here, you
sample something, but this combination logic changed too fast.
So D2 changed the whole time got violated because the input to the second register over here changed
too fast.
OK, you don't want that.
So there's what the potential.
Are 2T hold violation, so you should set your clock cycle time.
Actually this is different.
You should set things I should say that's going to be interesting such that you don't get into a
hold violation and it will be independent of the clock cycle time.
It turns out OK, yes.
When you say CL is too fast, you're talking about the contamination.
Exactly.
Yes, yeah.
OK.
And if the combination logic is too slow, then you might violate the set up time over here.
So basically, combination logic is too slow and you violated the set up time.
You'll get the wrong result.
So you should set your clock cycle time such that this doesn't happen.
OK, so we're going to look at both of these in sequence.
Let's first look at the set up time constraint because it's a bit easier to think about because it's
about the longest delay, right?
So essentially your safe timing depends on the maximum delay from R1 to R2.
Basically you you get the inputs from R1, you go through the combination logic and then you latch,
you capture the result at the rising edge.
So the input to R2 must be stable at least T set up before the clock edge, right?
So you have some your clock cycle.
In other words, your clock cycle should be greater than whatever delay is from here clock to queue,
right?
There is a propagation delay from clock to queue.
That's the maximum delay to read the data after the rising edge of the clock.
From here we we saw that right, That's the delay from clock to queue and then the maximum delay in
this combination logic which we calculated earlier for different combinational logic, TPD and the
set up time.
So your clock cycle time should be greater than the sum of these three.
OK, that makes sense.
Hopefully that's the maximum delay you get.
You need to read the data from the from R1, which is essentially propagation delay from clock to
queue.
You need to.
That's the maximum delay.
Your queue will be stable at that point, meaning the inputs to the combination logic and then those
inputs propagate through the combination logic, and there's a maximum delay through the combination
logic.
And then after that point, D2 is stable, but D2 needs to be stable longer than that to ensure that
the set up time doesn't get violated, right?
So this is essentially our clock cycle time.
If you think about it, we're doing useful work computation, assuming this is all doing useful work
in the combination logic, and we're kind of wasting some time to make sure that we can read the
inputs from the register and we can write the inputs to a register.
So this is also called wasted work.
This is also called sequencing overhead.
So this is essentially the overhead of a synchronous design.
Now, we talked about asynchronous versus synchronous, and asynchronous design would not have this
overhead, except you'll be going crazy designing that thing.
So that's a different overhead.
But in this case, there's some amount of time wasted every cycle, every clock cycle, because we need
to read the data from a register and write the data to some other register.
OK.
Due to timing requirements that we have, OK.
So let's take a look at this T set up constraint and design performance.
This is our critical path over here in the circuit that we have seen and essentially overall design
performance is determined by the critical path TPD, right, TPCQ&T set up, you cannot do much about
that.
You can reduce by designing a better flip flop, for example, right?
Designing better registers, better technology, etcetera.
Now, this determines your minimum clock.
Meaning maximum operating frequency.
Is one over frequency, right?
And if the critical pass is too long, the design will run slowly.
If the critical pass is too short, each cycle will do very little useful work, meaning most of the
cycle will be wasted in sequencing overhead.
So as TPD goes to 0, your clock cycle is dominated by TPC Q + T setup.
How good your flip flop, how fast your flip flops are, right?
So it can reduce the combinational logic delay that you have as much as possible by designing,
optimising your circuit a lot as we will see in pipelining, by reducing the stages to smaller and
smaller chunks.
But now you're dominated by your sequencing overhead.
OK, Hopefully that's clear.
That'll come back to us.
When we talk about pipelining, we'll design pipeline machines that look exactly like this.
You have an input register, combinational logic, an output register, which is the input to the next
stage in the pipeline.
Combinational logic, another output register, combinational logic, another output register.
So that'll be the pipeline we design, right?
And you will have a choice in how to divide all of that combinational logic.
That's going to do some amount of work whether you divide it into very small.
Delay portions, meaning many, many stages where each of them will do a little bit work, but the
sequencing overhead will be huge.
Or whether each stage does a lot of work where the sequencing overhead will be lower, but your clock
frequency will be also lower, right?
So it's good to think about that.
We're going to see more of this, so we're going to build up to pipelining.
OK, let's talk about hold time because this will reveal something interesting.
So set up time was not that interesting, right?
That's a maximum logic delay, and that's affected by the combinational logic as well as sequencing
elements.
Now, hold time is harder.
So in this case also it's harder to reason about, but I'll try to reason about it.
Safe timing depends on the minimum delay from R1 to R2, right?
So D2 meaning the R2 input over here must be stable for at least hold time after the clock edge,
right?
Meaning D2 must not change until T hold after the clock edge.
So what does this mean?
You have a minimum delay over here?
That's the contamination delay.
Somebody asked that question earlier, contamination delay from clock to queue.
Let's talk about the minimum delay at which the D2 can change contamination delay clock to queue
plus contamination delay through the logic.
And this should not be greater than T hold or this should be greater than T hold?
This should not be less than T hold, right?
If it's less than T hold, DD2 will change before the whole time requirement is satisfied.
So for this circuit to operate safely while satisfying the whole time requirement, the minimum delay
through the circuit which is reading the inputs and also operating on the inputs in the combination
logic together should be greater than the whole time of this register over here, OK?
So that's the requirement we need to satisfy.
And essentially if you actually change this equation a little bit, TCD combinational logic delay
should be greater than T hold minus TCCQ.
You can see that this actually completely independent of the clock.
It's really only depend on the characteristics of the sequential state elements that you're
building, meaning your registers, right?
OK.
So it becomes very hard, meaning it becomes very hard to fix.
You cannot just change the clock frequency, right?
If you actually violated this requirement for whatever reason because you didn't consider it, you
need to change the circuits.
You cannot just change the clock frequency.
You cannot just divide the clock, for example, like we discussed, or Yeah.
So basically, you need to be very careful to satisfy hold time constraints.
Now the good news is this doesn't happen very often, but this could happen if the combinational
logic delay, the combinational logic is very short actually.
And there are some paths in the combinational logic delay that can change very quickly, right.
So this is we're talking about contamination delay over here, not propagation delay, minimum delay.
OK, So this is the summary of sequential timing.
We have the clock to clock, clock to queue delay, contamination, minimum and maximum combinational
logic delays, again, minimum and maximum.
There's a set up time time that flip flop inputs must be stable before the next clock edge.
And there's a whole time time that flip flop inputs must be stable after the clock edge.
And then there's the clock.
And we've seen these pictures.
Now let's do some timing analysis.
So this is our sequential circuit.
You can see that there are 4 registers over here, ABCD.
Those are supplying inputs to this combinational circuit.
And there are two outputs that are latched in the next two registers, OK.
And here are timing characteristics that were given.
Somebody gave these.
OK, now let's take a look at how we should design the circuit to satisfy set up time and hold time
constraints.
So as we discussed, the combination logic delay should be greater than propagation delay, clock to
queue plus the maximum propagation delay through this combination logic plus the set up time of
these registers, right.
So we need to we need to calculate TPD and TCDTCD will be useful for the whole time constraints.
So TPD in this particular case is this is the critical path.
You go through three gates, each of them happened to be I guess per gate, 35 picoseconds, it's 105
picoseconds, OK Contamination delay is the minimum delay.
You go through one gate and there are two cases where this happens is 25 picoseconds.
OK, This is what we did with combination logic.
Let's do, let's apply to clock cycle time.
PCQ were given as 50 picoseconds.
So our clock to queue maximum delay is 50 picoseconds and then propagation delay of 105 picoseconds.
That's our critical path.
And then the setup time constraints is 60 picoseconds.
So our clock cycle time should be greater than 200.
In picoseconds in this particular case, meaning we cannot our frequency, our maximum frequency is
one over that which is 4.65 gigahertz.
OK, this is optimistic, of course, as we discussed, right?
Normally you add some timing margin.
We're not adding that.
We're not even talking about the wires over here.
OK, let's take a look at the hold time constraint.
Remember the hold time constraint, The minimum delay CCQ plus CD should be greater than the hold
time of this register, right?
So what is CCQ?
We're given that clock to queue delay, minimum delay 30 picoseconds and combination logic delay 25
picoseconds.
30 + 25 is 55.
And if you look at the hold time, hold time is specified for this register as 70 picoseconds.
Doesn't sound good.
So we didn't satisfy the hold time requirement.
So this circuit will probably not work.
Yes, yeah, 4.6 gigahertz.
I mean, this is just given, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's true.
Yes, these are these are actually in today's technology, you can do things much faster, Yes.
These are not meant to be today's technology.
OK, OK, So we didn't satisfy the whole time constraints and that's not depend on the clock
frequency.
So this fails.
So how do we fix the whole time violation?
I think your buffers come in over here.
Basically you add buffers and you do the timing analysis again after that.
The good news is these buffers are not on the critical path because they're actually on the minimum
delay path.
So it doesn't affect your critical path.
You can still clock things as fast, but it does so no change to Max frequency.
But now your CCQ plus CD becomes 80 picoseconds because you go through an inverter over here which
has ACD contamination delay of 25 picoseconds.
Am I correct?
Yes, I think so.
An inverter has a contamination delay same as this.
So 25 + 25 is 50 and then CCQ is 30.
So 80 picoseconds is greater than 70 picoseconds.
And you declare victory.
If you're comfortable with AD being larger large enough than 70, you may not be comfortable because
under all conditions you may not be.
That's, that's like 10% difference almost, right?
Not a lot.
Maybe you say, OK, I want to add more buffers, OK?
At some point, your critical path may start increasing depending on what you do.
OK, so This is why hold time is important, as you can see.
So hopefully you have a good idea of analysis right now.
We're going to complicate it more.
We assumed a lot of things.
You can add wires to this analysis, You can add temperature so it becomes more statistical, as I
said.
But one thing you we assumed that's really interesting is essentially related to wire delay in the
end.
But there's something called clock skew, meaning clocks have delay.
The clock does not reach all parts of the chip at the same time, right?
It's it reaches register one faster than register 2, for example.
Then the question is, how do you do the analysis right?
It's actually not that hard, but we'll do it.
It'll it'll essentially make our frequency lower.
Clock's queue is essentially a time difference between 2 clock edges.
So you have some clock source that's generating the clock.
The clock happens to arrive here faster.
It happens to take the scenic path to arrive here.
OK, so there's a long slow clock path.
As a result, clock arrives at point A faster than it arrives at point B.
The rising edge of the clock in one register happens earlier than the rising edge of the clock
happening in another register.
And this is real.
This is one of the beautiful chips that was designed in 1990s by Alpha Digital Equipment
Corporation.
It was it was the fastest processor of it's time, 500 megahertz.
And this is the distribution of the skew of clock.
When does the clock arrive to different parts of the chip?
You can see that there is a difference in skew.
And there's a reason why this looks like this because they had an interconnect H shaped
interconnect.
And I'm going to show you some examples of that interconnect.
So, so there's an interconnect that distributes the clock from the source with a lot of buffering to
the destinations.
OK, so let's take a look at let's revisit the set up time constraint with clock skew.
So now safe timing requires considering the worst case queue.
What does that mean?
That means that clock arrives at R2 before R1.
That's the worst case for the circuit for set up time.
Why?
Because set up time says that this D2.
Should be stable at least set up time before basically.
Basically the the D2 should arrive here early enough, right?
If this clock arrives here early and if this clock arrives here late, that means you have little
time, less time in this combination logic to operate on the inputs, right?
Does that make sense?
This if clock arrives into R2 earlier, R2 will latch things earlier then when this register will
latch things, meaning the inputs over here will be available later.
OK, so it's good to think about that.
So this is your pick your books picture over here.
So clock 1 rising edge happens later, which is this one.
Clock 2 rising edge happens earlier over here.
And this is also the important part over here.
So clock 1 inputs become available over here and there's a PCQ delay.
Yeah, signal essentially signal at D2 must must arrive at D2 earlier.
So there's a, the inputs over here are available right here.
So there's a PCQ delay for Q ones to stabilise and then there's a propagation delay over here
through the combination logic.
And there's a set up time that you need to obey and you need to take into account the SKU.
You need to wait for the SKU also.
So your clock cycle time should be greater than TPCQ plus TBD plus set up time plus the skew because
you need to account for the clock arriving at R2 earlier, OK?
So you're kind of compensating for that because clock arrives at R2 earlier, you have less time to
actually complete what you're doing.
So you need to increase the clock cycle time by that amount so that you don't match the wrong
result, OK, So that's the kind of the effective set up time.
Now you can think of it that way also, instead of having a skew like that you can incorporate into
the set up time.
That's one way of thinking about it.
Now, what this means is if your skew is higher, your clock frequency should be lower or cycle time
should be higher, OK.
That's why people try to distribute the clock as nicely and it's balanced as possible to different
parts of the chip so that the skew is lower, OK.
So they actually put a lot of effort into the distribution of the circuits, distribution of the
clock.
There's a clock distribution network essentially.
So let's look, let's take a look at the hold time.
Essentially safe timing now requires considering the worst case queue.
So hold time is kind of the opposite.
Basically DD2 should be stable for the for hold time after the rising edge of the clock, right?
Which becomes a problem if clock arrives at R2 after R1, right?
Because this increase the minimum required delay for this combination logic.
Let's take a look at that.
Clock arrives at R2 after it drives at R1.
Clock one has an earlier rising edge than clock 2 over here now, which means that the signal must
arrive at D2 later.
This effectively increase your T hold time.
Right before what we had was the combination or CCQ over here, TCCQ plus TCD, which is the minimum
delay until the two changes should be greater than the hold time.
But now you also have a clock skew, right?
Because clock arrives at R2 after R1, meaning this state transition will happen not at that point,
but skew later T skew later.
OK.
So I need to take that into account, which means that TCD plus TCCQ should be greater than T hold
plus T skew.
And this is now our effective hold time, OK.
So satisfying the hold time requirement also becomes more complicated because of because of clock
skew.
So I need to add more buffers essentially, right?
So a clock skew is not good for your clock frequency, your performance as well as your hold time
satisfaction, meaning that you need to add more area with more buffers to satisfy this.
This is the price of synchronous design.
Part of the price, part of the price was the sequencing overhead.
Now we're paying another price for synchronous design, which is clock skew, OK.
So essentially skew increases both T set up and T Holt is now is the increased sequencing overhead
less useful work done per cycle and designers must keep skew to a minimum.
So this requires intelligent clock network designs across the chip and people try to enable clock to
arrive at all locations roughly at the same time, which is a very difficult task with very large
chips today.
So what a lot of people try to do today is not global synchronous design, but more local
synchronous, but globally asynchronous design.
And there's some buffering that happens when you cross the clock domains.
You may actually think about different clocks enabling synchrony in different parts of the chip when
you when you when there are signals that.
Across different clock domains, you need to have some buffering, and the design of that buffering is
really, really critical in terms of correct operation.
But these are some example clock network designs that people have done in the past.
So there's an H3 design over here that kind of looks like this.
And Alpha 21 to 64 was kind of like that.
That's why you see these bumps in the middle.
OK, any questions?
Sounds like fun, right?
You know how to deal with all of these interesting issues when you design things.
OK, so we talked about timing.
Let's jump into verification.
We're not going to do a lot of analysis over here.
We're just going to talk about how to do verification.
Basically, how do you know that a circuit works?
Is it functionally correct?
Even if it's functionally correct, does the timing requirements get satisfied?
So basically the quick question becomes how can you test a circuit for functionality and timing?
And the answer, unfortunately here is mostly simulation tools.
Today there are some formal verification tools that people have developed to verify based on some
invariants.
They are not very scalable to the size of the hardware that we have today, unfortunately.
Imagine verifying these things, verifying A wafer scale processor with some SAT solvers, It takes a
lot of time.
Simulation also takes a lot of time, but people play a lot of tricks.
So in your labs, for example, you're going to do a lot of timing simulation using Vivado.
It's essentially a simulator.
And then there are lower level things, circuit simulation, which can enable help with timing as
well.
OK.
But the bigger question is testing large digital designs.
This is not an easy problem.
We're not going to solve it.
So we're going to cover, we're not going to cover everything over here and even existing systems
today because because things are difficult to design and difficult to verify.
There are faults that escape into the field.
We're going to talk about that in some later lectures, for example.
But sometimes people have found out, especially recently, that sometimes these processors compute
wrong values, right?
And this happens under a small fraction of conditions, maybe related to temperature, related to some
sort of environmental effects, related to some voltage spikes that happen that you cannot easily
control.
But people have found out that you get wrong results in a data centre.
If you have millions of these processors, for example, if one of them fails every month, you're
going to get a lot of failures over time, right?
So it's good to think about that.
So testing is still a problem and people are actually developing online testing methods to test
these processors while they're operating.
And these are actually happening right now because of the small size of the circuit.
But testing can be done also before you actually manufacture something, right?
And you're going to do that and you need to do that.
But even if after doing, even after doing testing today, things still fail.
OK, So testing is actually the most time consuming design stage that happens.
So 6070% of the cost of a processor cutting edge processor is testing today.
You need to do the functional correctness testing and you need to do the timing and power testing if
you care about power.
Now you do care about power because you have a maximum power requirement.
And if you're designing something cutting edge, you should not violate that, right?
So unfortunately, low level simulation is much slower than high level simulation.
So in general, people do both.
You check only functionality at a high level.
This is relatively fast simulation time.
It allows high code coverage.
It's easy to write and run tests and you check only timing, power, etcetera at low level.
At the circuit level, no functional testing of low level model and instead you reason about the
functional equivalence to high level model.
This is hard, but easier than testing logical functionality at a very low level, right?
OK, this will become more clear later.
So essentially we have tools to handle different levels of verification.
You have logic synthesis tools that's guarantee equivalence of high level logic and synthesised
circuit level description.
You trust them, Somebody needs to develop them.
They may not always be correct.
There are timing verification tools that check all circuit timings, and then there are design rule
checks that ensure that physical circuits are actually buildable.
That actually depends on what's manufacturable.
Basically, how far should my should this transistor be from this other transistor?
That's a design rule, for example.
We're not going to talk about that.
So the task of the logic designer is really to provide functional tests for logical correctness of
the design and also provide timing constraints like the desired operating frequency.
And then the tools or the circuit engineers will decide whether they can build it correctly.
So let's talk about functional verification.
We're going to talk about timing verification, which is much more difficult actually than functional
verification.
Functional verification is difficult.
Timing verification is much more difficult.
Power is even more difficult, basically.
OK, so essentially functional verification checks the logical correctness of the design or
functional correctness timing is typically ignored over here.
There are two primary approaches.
1 is logic simulation, which you're going to do a lot in your labs, and the other is formal
verification.
We're going to ignore formal verification over here.
There's a lot of research effort in this area and for small circuits it works, but for large
circuits it becomes harder.
We're going we're going to use Verilog for functional verification and I'm going to introduce
something called test bench phase functional test.
It's very similar to actually testing your software, but we're going to test hardware modules that
we developed.
So a test bench is a module created specifically to test a design, and the tested design is usually
called dot device under test.
People like these acronyms and it looks like this.
Basically, test bench, you have a test pattern generator that's exercise the inputs and that's
causes some change in the output and there's some output checking logic that checks whether the
outputs change correctly based on how the inputs were actuated.
I can, I think I've already said that.
So the question becomes, how do you provide the inputs?
You can have handcrafted values or you can automatically generate things, right?
There's something called automatic test pattern generation where people generate automatic test
patterns.
Regardless, this is not easy if you want to test every possible input combination.
And if you have thousands of inputs, that's like 2 of the 1000 different combinations that you're
testing, right?
OK, so you people, people usually do divide and conquer.
They actually test smaller modules and then they connect things.
But still it's not, we're going to see for a 64 bit adder, for example, you still have two to the 64
combinations, possible combinations for a given input, right?
And then you have two of those inputs.
OK, so test band checks the outputs of the data against values that you think are correct
handcrafted.
Or you have a golden design that is known to be bug free.
If you can design this, this is great.
So having this golden design at a high abstraction level may be very useful.
If you have a specially designed and validated processors in the past, this gives you an advantage.
Basically, experience helps over here.
OK so a test bench can be very lock code for example, or hardware, any hardware description language
code written to test other HDL modules.
Or it could be a circuit schematic used to test other circuit designs.
This is not designed for hardware synthesis.
This is just a test.
Basically, it runs in simulation.
You're going to do this a lot in your labs, like in Vivato.
We're not going to do a circuit simulation in this particular class, But if you want to go to the
lower level, you can simulate the circuits as well.
So we're going to use simulation only constructs.
For example, we're going to say in Verilog, wait for 10 nanoseconds, right?
We're not going to talk about voltage and current sources.
Basically, this is not going to be built.
So there are three kinds of test benches.
Simple, you do everything, input, output generation and error checking manually.
Self checking, input output generation is manual, error checking is automatic and automatic is the
best as you can see, ideally.
But there are trade-offs.
So let's take a look at different types of test benches that test this logic function.
So this is our silly function as you can see.
OK, And this is going to be our test bench.
So we basically have some simulation that we're going to run.
For example, the input, we set the value of Reg to zero and we wait for 10 nanoseconds and then
value of The Reg will be one.
That's how you manipulate or actuate the input.
And you observe by displaying a message saying this is our my output, for example, right?
You can you can print the output.
So let's develop the simple test bench relatively quickly.
We instantiate the silly function that I showed you earlier.
That's our design under test dot and apply hard coded inputs one at a time.
We set the inputs to all zeros, wait for 10, change C to one, wait for 10 nanoseconds.
Basically you keep applying, right?
This is one hard coded Test match looks terrible.
I mean, you could do it, right?
This is how you start programming, right?
And that's how I start programming by changing the values internally, right?
And this is a good way of starting also because you can check your waveform simulator and you can
look at the waveform diagrams and try to check whether you get the output correct.
This is a mess.
So you can manually check that output is correct at all times.
You don't want to do this.
OK, so it's easy to design.
You can easily test a few specific inputs like corner cases maybe, but it's not scalable clearly,
right?
You're not going to do this for two to the 32 input combinations and outputs must be checked
manually outside of simulation somehow either printfs or waveform signals.
Not good.
That's why people do self checking test benches which are not also enough.
But basically this is the idea over here.
You still manually supply the, manipulate the inputs, actuate the inputs and check whether the
output is correct.
After that you wait for some time and if output is not correct then you display.
But this test case failed OK.
So it's still easy to design, it's still easy to test a few specific inputs, but it's still not
scalable and easy to make an error in hard coded values.
OK, OK, I think I'm going to stop here because we have some more to discuss about testing.
We'll do that next week.
And next week we're going to also raise the abstraction level and talk about many interesting things
in architecture level.
OK, have a good weekend.